Guide to the Lowndes Maury Papers 1933-2001
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Lowndes Maury Papers
1933-2001
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana--Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 456
Maury, Lowndes, 1911-1975
10.0 linear feet
Lowndes Maury was a composer born in Montana who went on to work in Hollywood as a pianist, composer-arranger, and conductor. The collection consists mainly of his original compositions, prepared for a variety of clients and instrumentations.
Biographical Note
Lowndes Maury was born in Butte, Montana, in 1911 to H. Lowndes Maury and Anne Perkins Maury. He learned piano from his mother. In 1931, he graduated from the University of Montana--Missoula and went on to study piano and composition in Chicago. He also studied with Arnold Schoenberg in Boston.
Beginning in the 1930s, he built a career in Hollywood as a pianist, composer-arranger, and conductor. For a time he worked as a composer, arranger, pianist, and organist on twelve radio shows simultaneously, including the Eddie Cantor and Jack Haley shows Life with Father and The Life of Riley. He wrote film scores for Universal Pictures studios, for U.S. Air Force training films, and for the Mr. Magoo cartoons. He was also a contract pianist for Twentieth-Century Fox studios.
He also composed considerable "serious" music. Among his major works is the cantata Proud Music of the Storm (Walt Whitman), commissioned for the dedication of the new music building at the University of Montana in 1953. Other commissioned works included "Summer of Green," a rhapsody for alto flute and string orchestra, which was premiered by the New Zealand National Orchestra; "Night Life," for Kurt Reher, principal cellist with the Los Angeles Philharmonic Orchestra; and Man is My Song, a cantata written for the First Unitarian Church of Los Angeles.
In later years, he established the Lou Muary Piano School in North Hollywood. There his interest in the pedagogy of music resulted in two volumes of student and artist piano pieces called New Soundings. He also developed a new approach to music notation with Ralph Cromleigh, a computer analyst for Teledyne Systems, and brought out four volumes of Magic Lines and Spaces.
His Variations on a Beethoven Theme was commissioned and recorded by harpsichordist Igor Kipnis, and his violin sonata In Memory of the Korean War Dead was recorded by the composer with violinist Myron Sandler.
In 1964, he was cited by the Montana Territorial Centennial Committee for distinguished service in the field of original composition. In 1974, the University of Montana awarded him an honorary Doctor of Letters.
He died in 1975.
The collection contains biographical information, a small portion of Maury's correspondence about his works, press releases and a catalog of his published works, the original copies of the vast majority of his published compositions and some unpublished ones, and a posthumous audio recording of some major performances of his works. The collection documents the work of a mid-twentieth-century composer who worked in a variety of contexts: Hollywood, music education, and serious composition.
The collection is divided into five series:
Series I: Biographical, 1 folder, 1967-1976
Series II: Correspondence, 2 folders, 1970-1983
Series III: Speeches and Writings, 1 folder, undated
Series IV: Compositions, 9.5 linear feet, 1933-1970
Series V: Audio, 2 audio compact discs, 2001
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana--Missoula.
The majority of the collection was given to the Department of Music before transfer to the Archives. Other materials--including the original score to Proud Music of the Storm and the compact disc of Maury recordings--came directly to the Archives.
Gift of Lowndes Maury, 1953; transferred from Department of Music, 1984; gift of Mrs. Lowndes Maury, 1986; gift of Elizabeth H. Maury, 2003.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
University of Montana--Missoula--Alumni and alumnae
Piano--Study and teaching; Motion picture music
Music; Sound Recordings
Sound Recordings; Performing Arts
Sound Recordings; Performing Arts
Composers--United States
- Biographical, 1967-1976; Series I; 1 folder
  This series contains biographical descriptions of Lowndes Maury, one promotional piece and two different obituaries.
  - 1967-1976 (Box-folder 1/1)
- Correspondence, 1970-1983; Series II; 2 folders
  This file contains a small portion of Lowndes Maury's correspondence, some general exchanges from late in his life and a file regarding the premiere of his Concerto for English Words and Percussion.
  - General, 1978-1983 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Concerto for English Words and Percussion Premier, 1970 (Box-folder 1/3)
- Speeches and Writings, undated; Series III; 1 folder
  This series contains one folder of speeches, press releases, and a catalog of Lowndes Maury's compositions.
  - undated (Box-folder 1/4)
- Compositions, 1933-1970; Series IV; 9.5 linear feet
  This series consists of Maury's compositions for a variety of instruments and ensembles. All are either manuscript originals of scores or the master copies of ensemble parts. The series contains the majority of Maury's published output, as well as other works that may not have been published or performed.
  - Political Intrigue, Ballet, Pf.; The Celebration, 1946 and 1955 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Introduction and Sonatina for Oboe and String Orchestra, oboe, strings; Concerto for Piano and Orchestra, 1946 and 1947 (Box-folder 2/2)
  - "Summer of Green," Rhapsody for Alto Flute and String Orchestra, alto flute, str.; Passacaglia for Chamber Orchestra, 1963 and undated (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Proud Music of the Storm Cantata for chorus, soloists, narrator, 1953 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - "Man is My Song," Easter Cantata, undated (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Fanfare, violin, violincello, 2 horns, harp, pianoforte, 1967 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Concerto for English Words, Brass and Percussion, 1970 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Sabbath Eve Service for Cantor (baritone), Choir and Organ, 1949 (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Sonnet, "The World Is Too Much with Us", 1951 (Box-folder 2/9)
  - "A Christmas Carol;" "OBIT;" "Vertue;" "Lift Every Voice in Song;" Three Songs of Time and Its Passing, 1951-1968 (Box-folder 2/10)
  - The Queen's Sarabande, Quartet of Brass, 1941 (Box-folder 2/11)
  - Four Walks and a Fugue, Suite for String Quartet, 1942 (Box-folder 2/12)
  - The Birthday Divertimento, 1950 (Box-folder 2/13)
  - "Cock of the Walk," Sax Quartet, Avant Music, 1963 (Box-folder 2/14)
  - Scene de Ballet, for Alto Piccolo in A-flat and String Quartet, 1965 (Box-folder 2/15)
  - For Two Flutes, 1967 (Box-folder 2/16)
  - Changes for 7 Flutes, Avant Music, 1970 (Box-folder 2/17)
  - Elegy for Cello and Harp, undated (Box-folder 2/18)
  - Three Essays in Style, for Woodwind Quintet, undated (Box-folder 2/19)
  - "Tom Thumb and the Giant," Woodwind Quintet; Two Pieces for String Quartet, undated (Box-folder 2/20)
  - Pastorale, 1942 (Box-folder 2/21)
  - Concert Suites for Flute, Two Clarinets and Piano, 1942 (Box-folder 2/22)
  - "The Three Bears;" "Springtime Digressions", 1950 and 1961 (Box-folder 2/23)
  - "Speculations," for Piano and Three Strings, 1964 (Box-folder 2/24)
  - Sonatina for Violin, Bassoon, and Piano, 1968 (Box-folder 2/25)
  - Eleven Sketches for Piano Trio, 1968 (Box-folder 2/26)
  - "Pinocchio;" Quintette for String Quartette and Piano, undated (Box-folder 2/27)
  - "Summer of Green," Rhapsody for Alto Flute, Cello, and Piano, 1963 (Box-folder 2/28)
  - "Fiddle Boogie;" Serenade, 1945 and 1950 (Box-folder 2/29)
  - Sonata No. 1 for Violin and Piano, 1950 (Box-folder 2/30)
  - Sonata for Violin and Piano: In Memory of the Korean War Dead, 1950 and 1968 (Box-folder 2/31)
  - Songs Without Words for Clarinet and Piano; "Summer of Green," Rhapsody for Alto Flute and Piano; "Reflection," for Flute and Piano, Antransa Music, 1958-1965 (Box-folder 2/32)
  - Songs Without Words for Clarinet and Piano or Viola and Piano, Antransa Music; Flute Now, Six original compositions plus six arrangements of popular tunes, 1965 and 1970 (Box-folder 2/33)
  - Basque Dance; Moto Perpetuo; "Night Life," for Cello and Pinao or Viola and Piano, undated (Box-folder 2/34)
  - Prelude and Fugue for Trombone and Piano; "Reflection," for Flute and Harpsichord, undated (Box-folder 2/35)
  - "Serious Cereal," fl.; "Lament, fl., Avant Music; Suite for the Solo Cello, 1958-1975 (Box-folder 2/36)
  - "On Quiet Waters," Pf., "Music Box," pf.; Three Voice Invention; "A Waltzing Fugue", 1939-1949 (Box-folder 2/37)
  - Three Affirmations; Chorale Aria; Three Poets; "Mountain in the West;" "Space Trip;" Earliest Suite for Keyboard Instruments, 1962-1971 and undated (Box-folder 2/38)
  - Six Changes for Two Pianos; "A Song of the Plains;" Three Pieces for Piano Solo; Variations for Harpsichord on a Beethoven Theme; "Wind Sweep", undated (Box-folder 2/39)
  - "When Daisies Pied and Violets Blue;" Three Miniatures/"A Lover's Day;" "The WIND;" Three Songs of William Blake, 1938-1948 and undated (Box-folder 2/40)
  - Five Rilke Songs from "The Book of Hours", 1948 (Box-folder 2/41)
  - "Nocturne;" "Some Girls Are Prettier;" "Ring Out, Wild Bells;" "Cynara;" Three Songs; Arabesque, 1950-1974 and undated (Box-folder 2/42)
  - "Farandole;" "Landscape;" "Music, When Soft Voices Die;" "Tobacco's but an Indian Weed;" Three Elemental Songs, 1968 and undated (Box-folder 2/43)
  - Sonatina, undated (Box-folder 3/1)
  - Summer of Green, undated (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Flute Now, 1970 (Box-folder 3/3)
  - Sonata for Flute and Piano, undated (Box-folder 3/4)
  - Arabesque, undated (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Scherzo, 1933 (Box-folder 3/6)
  - Brandenburg Concerto No. 3, arranged for two pianos, 1933 (Box-folder 3/7)
  - Three Voices Invention, 1942 (Box-folder 3/8)
  - Three Poets, undated (Box-folder 3/9)
  - New Surroundings, undated (Box-folder 3/10)
  - Quiet River, undated (Box-folder 3/11)
  - Variations for Harpsichord on a Beetohoven Theme, undated (Box-folder 3/12)
  - Three Miniatures, "A Lover's Day", 1938 (Box-folder 3/13)
  - Five Songs, undated (Box-folder 3/14)
  - Five Rilke Songs, undated (Box-folder 3/15)
  - Nocturne, undated (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Ring Out, Wild Bells, 1943 (Box-folder 4/2)
  - Cynara, 1952 (Box-folder 4/3)
  - The Dog and the Bone, undated (Box-folder 4/4)
  - Psalm 139: I Will Praise Thee, 1951 (Box-folder 4/5)
  - A Christmas Carol, 1951 (Box-folder 4/6)
  - Vertue, 1952 (Box-folder 4/7)
  - Of Time and Its Passing, undated (Box-folder 4/8)
  - Four Walks and a Fugue, undated (Box-folder 4/9)
  - The Birthday Divertimento, undated (Box-folder 4/10)
  - Three Contemporary Saxophone Quartets, undated (Box-folder 4/11)
  - Changes for 7 Flutes, undated (Box-folder 4/12)
  - Chaconne for Flute and Three Guitars, undated (Box-folder 4/13)
  - Cock of the Walk, undated (Box-folder 4/14)
  - Scarlattina, undated (Box-folder 4/15)
  - Three American Songs, undated (Box-folder 5/1)
  - Three Essays in Style, undated (Box-folder 5/2)
  - Tom Thumb and the Giant, undated (Box-folder 5/3)
  - Two Pieces for String Quartet, undated (Box-folder 5/4)
  - "Introduction", undated (Box-folder 5/5)
  - "Allegro Molto", undated (Box-folder 5/6)
  - Man is My Song, undated (Box-folder 5/7)
  - Fanfare, undated (Box-folder 5/8)
  - Goddesses, 1972 (Box-folder 5/9)
  - Peace is Man's Supremest Good, undated (Box-folder 5/10)
  - Let the Rail-Splitter Awake, undated (Box-folder 5/11)
  - Scene de Ballet, undated (Box-folder 5/12)
  - Pastorale, undated (Box-folder 5/13)
  - Concert Suite for Flute, Two Clarinets and Piano, undated (Box-folder 5/14)
  - The Three Bears, undated (Box-folder 5/15)
  - "Springtime Digressions", 1961 (Box-folder 5/16)
  - Speculations, 1964 (Box-folder 5/17)
  - Eleven Sketches for Piano Trio, undated (Box-folder 5/18)
  - Pinocchio, undated (Box-folder 6/1)
  - Quintet for String Quartet Piano, undated (Box-folder 6/2)
  - Fiddle Boogie, undated (Box-folder 6/3)
  - Serenade, undated (Box-folder 6/4)
  - Sonata for Violin and Piano, undated (Box-folder 6/5)
  - Song Without Words, undated (Box-folder 6/6)
  - Reflection, undated (Box-folder 6/7)
  - Night Life, undated (Box-folder 6/8)
  - Homage to Lorca, undated (Box-folder 6/9)
  - A Song of the Plains, undated (Box-folder 6/10)
  - When Daisies Pied and Violets Blue, undated (Box-folder 6/11)
  - Five Rilke Songs from "The Book of Hours", undated (Box-folder 6/12)
  - Cynara, undated (Box-folder 6/13)
  - Three Elemental Songs, undated (Box-folder 6/14)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Piano reduction, sections 1-7, 2 copies, 1953 (Box-folder 6/15)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Full score for overture, 1953 (Box-folder 6/16)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Narrator part, 1953 (Box-folder 6/17)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Piano reduction, complete, bound, 2 copies, 1953 (Box-folder 6/18)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Soprano Solo, 1953 (Box-folder 7/1)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Alto Solo, 1953 (Box-folder 7/2)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Tenor Solo, 1953 (Box-folder 7/3)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Bass Solo, 1953 (Box-folder 7/4)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Orchestral parts, 1953 (Box-folder 7/5)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Orchestral parts, 1953 (Box-folder 7/6)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Orchestral parts, violin I, 1953 (Box-folder 8/1)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Orchestral parts, violin II, 1953 (Box-folder 8/2)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Orchestral parts, violin II, 1953 (Box-folder 8/3)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Orchestral parts, viola, 1953 (Box-folder 9/1)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Orchestral parts, viola, 1953 (Box-folder 9/2)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Orchestral parts, viola, 1953 (Box-folder 9/3)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Orchestral parts, cello, 1953 (Box-folder 10/1)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Orchestral parts, cello, 1953 (Box-folder 10/2)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Orchestral parts, bass, 1953 (Box-folder 10/3)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Orchestral parts, flute I, II, III, 1953 (Box-folder 11/1)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Orchestral parts, Oboe I, II, III, 1953 (Box-folder 11/2)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Orchestral parts, Clarinet I, II, Bass Clarinet, 1953 (Box-folder 11/3)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Orchestral parts, Basson I and II, 1953 (Box-folder 11/4)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Orchestral parts, Horn I, II, III, IV, 1953 (Box-folder 11/5)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Orchestral parts, Trumpet I, II, III, 1953 (Box-folder 11/6)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Orchestral parts, Trombone I and II, Tuba, 1953 (Box-folder 11/7)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Orchestral parts, Percussion I and II, Timpani, and Piano, 1953 (Box-folder 11/8)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Orchestral parts, incomplete choral arrangement, 1953 (Box-folder 12/1)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Orchestral parts, copies of choral arrangement, 1953 (Box-folder 13/1)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Orchestral parts, 15 copies of choral arrangement, 1953 (Box-folder 14/1)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Orchestral parts, 17 copies of choral arrangement, 1953 (Box-folder 15/1)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Orchestral parts, 16 copies of choral arrangement, 1953 (Box-folder 16/1)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Orchestral parts, 25 copies of choral arrangment, 1953 (Box-folder 17/1)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Orchestral parts, 24 copies of choral arrangment, 1953 (Box-folder 18/1)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Orchestral parts, 24 copies of the choral arrangement, 1953 (Box-folder 19/1)
  - Pround Music of the Storm, Orchestral parts, 23 copies of the choral arrangement, 1953 (Box-folder 20/1)
  - Proud Music of the Storm, original, handwritten copy, 1955 (Box-folder 29OS/4)
  - Concerto for English Word, Brass, and Percussion, 1970 (Box-folder 21/1)
  - Libertto, 1970 (Box-folder 21/2)
  - Complete rehersal piano parts, 2 sets, 1970 (Box-folder 21/3)
  - Complete brass and percussion parts: Trumpets-4, Horns-4, Trombones-2, Bass Trombone-1, Tubas-2, Percussion-5, 1970 (Box-folder 21/4)
  - Full Score, 1970 (Box-folder 21/5)
  - Concerto for English Words, Brass, and Percussion Chorus parts, 1970 (Box-folder 22/1)
  - Concerto for English Words, Brass, and Percussion Chorus parts, 1970 (Box-folder 22/2)
  - Concerto for English Words, Brass, and Percussion Chorus parts, 1970 (Box-folder 22/3)
  - Concerto for English Words, Brass, and Percussion Chorus parts, 1970 (Box-folder 23/1)
  - Concerto for English Words, Brass, and Percussion Chorus parts, 1970 (Box-folder 23/2)
  - Concerto for English Words, Brass, and Percussion Chorus parts, 1970 (Box-folder 23/3)
  - Concerto for English Words, Brass, and Percussion Chorus parts, 1970 (Box-folder 24/1)
  - Concerto for English Words, Brass, and Percussion Chorus parts, 1970 (Box-folder 24/2)
  - Concerto for English Words, Brass, and Percussion Chorus parts, 1970 (Box-folder 24/3)
  - Concerto for English Words, Brass, and Percussion Chorus parts, 1970 (Box-folder 25/1)
  - Concerto for English Words, Brass, and Percussion Chorus parts, 1970 (Box-folder 25/2)
  - Concerto for English Words, Brass, and Percussion Chorus parts, 1970 (Box-folder 25/3)
  - Concerto for English Words, Brass, and Percussion Chorus parts, 1970 (Box-folder 26/1)
  - Concerto for English Words, Brass, and Percussion Chorus parts, 1970 (Box-folder 26/2)
  - Concerto for English Words, Brass, and Percussion Chorus parts, 1970 (Box-folder 26/3)
  - Concerto for English Words, Brass, and Percussion Chorus parts, 1970 (Box-folder 27/1)
  - Concerto for English Words, Brass, and Percussion Chorus parts, 1970 (Box-folder 27/2)
  - Concerto for English Words, Brass, and Percussion Chorus parts, 1970 (Box-folder 27/3)
  - Concerto for English Words, Brass, and Percussion printed and bound copy, 1970 (Box-folder 29OS/3)
  - The Celebration, 1955 (Box-folder 28/1)
  - Libretto, 1955 (Box-folder 28/2)
  - Piano Scores, 2, 1955 (Box-folder 28/3)
  - Orchestral parts: flute, oboe, clarinet-2, bassoon, horn, trumpet, trombone, percussion-2, violin A-2, violin B-2, violin C-2, viola-2, viola-2, cello-2, bass-2, piano/vocal - "Serenade" movement-2, 1955 (Box-folder 28/4)
- Audio, 2001; Series V; 2 audio compact discs
  These audio recordings are collection of Lowndes Maury's works recorded during his lifetime. In 2001, these recordings were digitally re-mastered and put on compact discs by his daughter, Elizabeth H. Maury.
  - Lowndes Maury Recording Project, Volume 1, 2001 (Box-folder 29OS/1)
  - Lowndes Maury Recording Project, Volume 2, 2001 (Box-folder 29OS/2)